<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some considerations tending to the undeceiving those, whose judgements are misinformed by politique protestations, declarations, &amp;c. Being a necessary discourse for the present times, concerning the unseasonable difference between the Protestant and the Puritan.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W691A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E126_45</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871454</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E126[45])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some considerations tending to the undeceiving those, whose judgements are misinformed by politique protestations, declarations, &amp;c. Being a necessary discourse for the present times, concerning the unseasonable difference between the Protestant and the Puritan.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Walwyn. Cf. McMichael and Taft, The writings of William Walwyn, pp.62-3.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novemb: the 10th 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156186:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>SOME CONSIDERATIONS Tending to the undeceiving thoſe, whoſe judgements are miſinformed by <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique Proteſtations, Declarations, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Being a neceſſary diſcourſe for the preſent times, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the unſeaſonable difference between the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and the PURITAN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE end of the Parliaments conſultations, and actions, is to free the Kingdome (the care whereof is to them by the Kingdome committed) from all thoſe heavy tyrannies and oppreſſions which for many yeares, againſt expreſſe Lawes, and cautions to the contrary, have ſurrounded and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed the Kingdome, all which, if wee have not a deſire to let them ſlip our memories, the Parliaments firſt Remonſtrance will fully preſent unto us. Thoſe men that do oppoſe the Parliament, are generally ſuch as ſome way or other have thrived under thoſe preſſures, as being made inſtruments and actors in them, or elſe being addicted to vice and looſeneſſe, found that connivence and indulgence, then which, in times more reformed they cannot expect. Thoſe men that doe now ſide with, and aſſiſt the Parliament, are ſuch as in thoſe corrupt times were trodden under foot, ſuch as were vext and impoveriſht by inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Courts, and Court-officers, forc't againſt conſcience to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156186:2"/>to the breach of the Sabbath, compelled to flie their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, or ſeparate from the Church, by inducing vaine and empty Ceremonies, which direct our mindes from conſideration of Gods love to us in Chriſt, and are utterly inconſiſtent with the true, and ſpirituall worſhip of God; and indeed therefore preſſed upon us, that thereby their friends might be knowne from their foes, the eaſie to be abuſed from the more difficult, that they might be imbraced, and have all encouragements both from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and men of high places; and theſe diſgraced, proſecuted, and though of never ſo honeſt lives, yet if in all things not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable, ſcandalled, and made odious: Ceremonies were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore too preſſed upon us, that by them the Church becomming more pompous, and outwardly ſpecious, the Clergy (by whom the Stateſmen were eſpecially to doe their ill intended worke) might win greater eſteeme, and grow more and more reverenced by the people, who ſeldome they know dive into the reaſons of things, but are uſually carryed away by outward ſhewes and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances. The Parliaments other friends are ſuch as have beene tormented with the permitted corruption of Lawyers, thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Locuſts, no leſſe ravening then the Aegyprian ones that overſpread that Land; ſuch likewiſe as had loſt the liberty of Trade, for the gaining of which, they ſerved a long and tedious apprenticeſhip, by unlawfull engroſſments, and Patents; and all the multitude of good men, who are ſenſible either by their owne, or their nighbours ſufferings, of the injuries of former times, or deſirous to prevent and divert our oppreſſion and ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the future: Now as it is a notable policy of evill men, though of quite different and oppoſite conditions to combine and aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate together againſt all that oppoſe them, bearing with, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by any thing for the preſent, though at other times much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtfull. So how much more does it behove the honeſt men of this Kingdome, who are likely to taſte equally the ſweetes of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, or the bitter pills of ſlavery, how ever they may be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded otherwiſe for the preſent, to unite themſelves heart and hand, to joyne together as one man, againſt all thoſe whom they ſhall diſcerne either to oppoſe the Parliament, or endeavour to raiſe diviſions and differences among themſelves. The only way for our enemies to doe their worke, is not by ſtrength, and force of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156186:2"/>Armes, for what ever their brags be, and how great ſoever their boaſts by which they would ſeeme to have what they have not, that thereby they may encourage their party, and diſhearten their adverſaries, yet indeed their forces are but ſmall, their proviſions ſcanty, their meanes and mony only ſupplyed by rapine, which cannot be laſting, having neither Forts, nor Shipping, ſo that it cannot be that by ſtrong hand they ſhould have any hope to doe their worke: No certainly, and yet notwithſtanding they ſtill dare to hold up the Cudgels, ſeeme as confident as ever, beare up, as if the world were of their ſide; what ſhould be the reaſons hereof; reaſons there are, we muſt perſwade our ſelves, it is not to be ſuppoſed that they are foole-hardy, or that the ſenſe of their many miſchiefes have made them deſperate, becauſe paſt hope of reconcilement (though they well may) their Councels are notable, and ſurely come not ſhort of the moſt able the world affords, their ſubtleties exceeds the Foxes, or the Serpents, Romes or Spaines; whoſe moſt damnable glory it is, that from meane beginnings they, by their wits eſpecially, have raiſed themſelves to the moſt extended tyrannies in the Chriſtian world: and why ſhould our politique enemies then deſpaire? Since their wits are as quick, their conſciences as deeply pained and ſenceleſſe, many of our people as eaſie to be deluded as ever men were, having the aſſiſtance of former contrivances in making men ſlaves, furniſhed with Machiavils, and<note n="*" place="margin">The Author of the Machivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian plot.</note> 
               <hi>Staffords</hi> inſtructions from <hi>Florence,</hi> with all the aſſiſtance Romes conſiſtory, or Spaines can afford: and what force cannot doe, deceit may: a ſubtill deceitfull Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may doe much more miſchief then an Army, the one kills men outright, and ſo leaves them unſerviceable for both ſides, but deceitfull words, when for want of conſideration, unſettledneſſe of judgement, and weake information, they captivate men, they make them not only dead to good mens aſſiſtance, and their Countries ſervice, but promoters likewiſe of their deluders inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, to the inſenſible ruine and ſlavery of their brethren, and in concluſion, of themſelves. Deceits and deluſions are the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall weapons with which the evill Counſellors now fight; by which they ſubdue and captivate the underſtandings and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men; to ſcatter theſe, they hurry about from one County into another, and there at Aſſiſes, and other forc't Aſſemblies
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156186:3"/>practiſe, in one place they colour and gloſe over their owne evill actions, with ſeeming pretences of Law, Religion: in another, they ſcandalize and traduce the Parliament, for as they cannot want paint to make fowle and unſightly actions ſeeme faire and ſpecious, ſo neither can they want dirt and mire to disfigure the beſt formed, and moſt honeſt enterprizes in the world; words are never defective to make evill ſeeme good, and good evill: what villany was there ever committed, or what injuſtice, but words and pretences might be found to juſtifie it: Monopolies were once pleaded legall, and very wholeſome for the people, we were once perſwaded Ship-money was lawfull, and now Commiſſion of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray; if unjuſt things were offered to us, as they are, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe and artificiall covering, they would appeare ſo odious, as that each man would cry out upon them, and therefore it is a high point of policy to make the worſt things ſhew faireſt, ſpeake beſt, when they intend moſt miſchiefe. In other Counties the people were thanked for their affections and aſſiſtance, when they found them wiſer then to yeeld any, and when they were driven by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to a place, they would ſeeme to be invited by love, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of compliance, when God knowes in many places they found it much otherwiſe, and would likewiſe elſewhere too, but that the people were neceſſitated to their aſſiſtance by force, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then forward, out of any liking. Well, their policies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions are moſt numerous, and every day increaſing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behoves every wiſe man to ſtand upon his guard, to be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and watchfull that he be not apprehended by their fubtilties: in nothing there is required greater care, their invaſions being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, and having once ſeiſed upon a man, he no longer diſlikes, but approves of them, they force a man to love what ere whiles he hated, what he but now cryed downe, to plead for, and not to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, becauſe his intentions are honeſt, and he meanes no ill, that he is even againſt his knowledge his Countries enemy: Hee that can give any cautions how to reſiſt their wyles, or ſhew wherein we are already ſeduced by our cunning adverſaries, doth doe very good ſervice to his Country, and deſerves to be heard; this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was written principally for that end, namely, to diſcover to all good men how they have ſuffered themſelves to be wrought upon by the adverſary in a caſe very conſiderable, and thereby,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156186:3"/>though they obſerve it not, are become friends to their Countries chiefe foes, and foes to their principall friends. The worke of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Counſellors, as it is to unite and ioyne together their friends, ſo is it likewiſe to ſeparate and divide their foes amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: all ſuch are their foes as truly love their owne liberty, and deſire to free themſelves from their inſulting tyranny: it muſt needs be very advantagious to them, if by any meanes they can divide theſe, for being diſioyned, they cannot poſſibly be ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull againſt them as otherwiſe they would be, did they continue at union: now amongſt many other wayes that they have uſed to accompliſh this end, there is not one hath been more effectuall then in raiſing, and cheriſhing differences concerning formes and circumſtances about Religion, that ſo ſetting them together by the eares about ſhadowes, they may in the meane time ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your ſubſtance: there is no difference they full well know is ſo permanent, as that which any way touches upon Religion, and therefore like cunning Pioners, have lighted upon what is likely to make the greateſt breach, which by continuall plying the work, the difference dayly increaſing, it is much to be feared that all the paines the Parliament takes, the aſſiſtance of good men, the haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards of our reſolute ſouldiers, or whatever endeavours elſe are uſed for the accompliſhing of good mens deſires, will by this one difference, if continued, be utterly fruſtrate, and come to naught: for it is almoſt come to that paſſe, that the Puritan and Sectaries, as they are called, are more odious to the Proteſtant, then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, Malignant, or Papiſt: all our diſcourſes are diverted now by the cunning practiſe of the Polititian from our forepaſt cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, plots, and conſpiracies of lewd men, from thinking what will be the beſt wayes to ſpeed and advantage our undertakings for our liberty, to raylings againſt the Puritan, to croſſe and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Puritan, to provoke him by many inſolencies, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts to diſorders, and then to inveigh with all bitterneſſe againſt his diſorders: if at ſuch times as theſe, when ſo great a worke is in hand, as the freeing of us from ſlavery, we can be ſo drowzily fottiſh as to neglect that, for the ſatisfying our giddy and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering humour, what can be ſaid of us, but that our fancy is dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to us then our liberty, that we care not what goes to racke, though it be our ſubſtantiall Religion, Lawes, and Liberties, ſo we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156186:4"/>but pleaſe our ſelves in crying downe our Brethren, becauſe they are either more zealous, or elſe more ſcrupulous then our ſelves: Theſe things my friends, (for all good men are ſuch) doe ſhew that you are not conſiderate, nor doe not ſufficiently beare in mind what was told you in the Parliaments firſt Remonſtrance, that it was (and ſtill is) one of the principall workes of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemy, to ſow diviſion between the Proteſtant and Puritan, you have beene too eaſie, and quickly wrought upon by him for the accompliſhing that worke: I would to God you would lay it to heart; the Puritan intends no miſchiefe to any, you may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your ſelves he does not: if you inquire you ſhall finde that they had no hand in our former oppreſſions, they were no main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of any unjuſt courſes, or Courts, unleſſe by thoſe many fines which were extorted from them, for that they of all men had the courage to withſtand their injuries: wee heare of daily plunderings, rapes, and murthers of the Cavaliers, women with child runne through, and many other butcheries, and yet wee paſſe by theſe, as if by no intereſt they concerned us, and let flie our ſpeeches only againſt the Puritan for plucking a raile downe, or a paire of Organs, a Surplice, Crucifix, or painted window, which are indeed no way conducible to the ſubſtantiall worſhip of God, and yet retained by the ill diſpoſed Clergy, as fuell to yeeld matter to that diſcord they would continue amongſt you: See how much too blame we are, ſee how exceedingly the politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian has deluded us, that we ſhould doe thus, and yet ſee not that we doe unwiſely. If thy brother bee weake and thou ſtrong, beare with his weakeneſſe, or if the Puritan eſteerne thee weake, and himſelfe ſtrong, it will be a good leſſon to him; if wee be ſtrong we ſhould beare with them that are weake; if we are weake we ſhould not judge them that are ſtrong, it will be no ſhame for any one to take the Apoſtles advice; let not ſlight and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things divide our affections; let them not eſpecially when ſubſtantiall things lie at the ſtake; it is all one as if our enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the field with full purpoſe and ſpeed to deſtroy us, wee ſhould turne aſide to exclaime againſt a man that flung dirt upon us or laught at us: and wholly neglect altogether to defend our ſelves: what a ſhame will it be unto us, when hereafter it is ſaid that the Engliſh might have freed themſelves from oppreſſion and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156186:4"/>ſlavery, but that in the doing of it they neglected their common enemy, and fell at variance among themſelves for trifles. Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and other things that occaſion difference, are ſtickled for by the Proteſtant, not for that they thinke them neceſſary, for ſurely unleſſe it be for ſome indirect end they cannot be urged to be ſo, but for that they are not yet taken downe by authoritie: The Puritan they would have them taken away for that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them vaine, unwarrantable by Gods Word, reliques of the Romiſh Religion not throughly purged away, and therefore they deſire they ſhould be left off by us, which are the principall cauſe of their ſeparation from us: In all differences to bee unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to reconcile, ſhewes not a ſpirit of love, which Chriſtians ſhould ever be poſſeſt withall, but of pride and contention, the Proteſtant hath not the engagements of conſcience upon him, as the Puritan has, and therefore may the eaſier beare with the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans infirmities, if meat offend my weake brother I will eate no meat as long as I live, what an excellent thing were it if we could have that hold faſt over our ſelves that the Apoſtle had to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine from any thing how pleaſant and deare ſoever unto us, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then give any offence, or occaſion any difference betweene our ſelves and weake brethren: let every man thinke of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering this queſtion to himſelfe: whether if lewd men doe get the better over the Parliament and honeſt men of the Kingdome, either Proteſtant or Puritan are likely to be any other but ſlaves: Certainly if any of them doe perſwade themſelves otherwiſe, they are like the ſtiffe-necked and unweildy Hebrewes, that wiſht they were ſlaves in <hi>Egypt</hi> againe, where the much loved Fleſh pots were, for that it was troubleſome and dangerous paſſing through the <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> into <hi>Canaan,</hi> a land of plenty and laſting liberty. Be not deceived with deluding thoughts of former times, when plenty covered our oppreſſions, and becauſe of peace wee could not ſee our ſlavery: it was a time when ſuch as <hi>Buckingham, Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> domineering Biſhops, corrupt and lawleſſe Judges, grew rich and potent: when <hi>Courts</hi> Minions for no ſervices but ſlavery and luxury were exalted, when offices were not conferred on foreſeene venue and honeſt deſert, but were bought and ſold; when honours that ought to be the rewards of venue, were by gold purchaſed, and they onely deemed fit Subjects for both, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156186:5"/>were eaſie to be corrupted, ſuch as had ſtupid conſciences, &amp; would ſuffer their matters to undertak any diſhoneſt employment. He that wiſhes for former times wiſhes for ſuch times wherein it had beene much better for a man to let goe his right or inheritance, though never ſo apparantly his, to any varlet that would have laid but any colorable claime to it, rather then have bin wurried by Court Maſtives, &amp; eaten to the bare bones by griping Judges and avari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Lawyers; wherein a murder in one man was not ſo much puniſhed as a word in another, wherein a poore man was hanged for ſtealing food for his neceſſitie, and a luxurious Courtier of whom the world was never like to have any other fruits but oathes and ſtabbes, could be pardoned after the killing the ſecond or third man: wherein in a word, knaves were ſet upon honeſt mens ſhoulders, all looſeneſſe was countenanced, and vertue and pietie quite out of faſhion: In theſe times, who kept themſelves ſo ſteddy as the Puritan, who oppoſed againſt thoſe exorbitant cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and by that meanes who ſmarted more then they: ſure I I thinke their ſufferings are yet in each mans memory, who but they, or they eſpecially withſtood all Church innovations, and other taxes and impoſitions, for which both the Biſhops and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, as alſo the corrupt Stateſman, and Projector were their profeſt and open enemies, and even then to make them odious, invented ridiculous names for them, and ſtudied ſcurrilous tales and jeſts againſt them, and ever ſigned new devices concerning them, to direct our thoughts from our every dayes oppreſſions, to ſport at the Puritan. The wayes of wicked men are like the way of a Ship in the Sea, ſo quick and ſpeedily covered, that without much obſervancy we cannot trace them: So that we ſee theſe endeavors to make the Puritan odious is no new policy, nor yet the reaſons why it is endeavored, and how great a blemiſh it is unto our judgement, that though this deceit hath beene ſo long in practiſe, and ſo apparently miſchievous to good, and advantageous to bad men, we ſhould not yet diſcover it, or being diſcovered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared unto us, wee ſhould not lay it to heart, and endeavor to avoid it. Sure I thinke there is no more evident marke of our diſaffections to the Parliament, then our invectives againſt the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan, whom the Parliament and all good men ought in all reaſon to eſteeme well of, for that they have beene ſo abundant in their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156186:5"/>contributions, ſo forward in their ſervices, ſo neglective of their private, to advance that neceſſary and moſt allowable work, both by God and all reaſonable men in the world, of freeing us and our poſterity from loathſome Tyranny and oppreſſion: whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faults the Puritan hath, this is not a time to caſt them in his diſh, neither are we certaine that they are faults, we have but ſo digeſted them to our ſelves, what he can ſay for himſelf, in his own juſtification, is not yet heard, nor is there yet a time of hearing: we may aſſure our ſelves that the Parliament will endeavour all that poſſible they can to give all ſorts of men that will not prove ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, and unſatisfiable, the beſt and largeſt ſatisfaction: If they ſhould now goe about it, or if they ſhould at any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore have enterpriſed it, they might in the meane time have had their throats cut, it is and hath been the endeavour of the Kings evill adviſers, to urge them alwayes to the ſettlement of the Church, a worke they know requires much time for the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it, and ſo muſt of neceſſity have diverted all conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and proviſions for their ſafety, when in the meane time thoſe adviſers would have been moſt active and vigilant, loſing no jot of time, nor balking no opportunity or advantage to have fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves, made a prey of the Parliament, and in their ruines have buryed all thats neer &amp; deer unto us: We ſee, that though the Parliament have only intended one buſineſs, the defence and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of themſelves, and the Kingdome, ſo great oppoſition hath yet been made, and ſo difficult a worke have they found it, that there is no man can ſay they are too forward: and therefore if we will not willfully make our ſelves a prey to our common enemy, let us reſolve for the time to come firmly to unite our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections beyond the policy of evill-witted men to diſſolve: let thoſe whom the malignant and inconſiderate call Puritans, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour all that they can poſſibly, to give no offence to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, and let the Proteſtant be ſlow in taking any at the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan: the Puritan indeed is too blame in his not obſerving all hee can to win by love, gentle behaviour, ſuch as differ from him in opinion, in not endeavouring all he can to bridle his paſſion, and not ſuffer his different opinion to coole his love and affection to other men: what? We have all need one of another, and till ſuch time things are throughly canvaſſed, and examined (how ever
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156186:6"/>each man concludes himſelfe to be in the right (we know we are partiall to our ſelves) he may be miſtaken, and upon better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which as yet he ſees not may alter his judgement and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc't; let us unite together as one man to the extirpation of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and diſcovered enemies both of our ſubſtantiall Religion, our lawes, and liberties, that ſo all being quiet, and wee aſſuredly free-men, all ſtratagems diſſolved, and the Sunne of peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine appearing, the Church may be ſo purged and ſo religiouſly ſetled, that the Puritan may have no cauſe of ſeperation (which cannot be according to his deſire but that to which by the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of his conſcience he is neceſſitated too) and ſo may be no longer an eyeſore and diſtaſtfull to the Proteſtant, but both may with mutuall joy and peace of conſcience joyne together in praiſes and thankſgivings to that God, who by the free, and alone death of his Sonne attoned and reconciled us to himſelfe, end in giving us his Sonne hath together with him given us all things alſo. But to what purpoſe will this, or other diſcourſes of this nature be, when there is a ſort of people in this kingdome, who make it their ſtudy and bend all their endeavours for to encreaſe and enlarge this difference: and yet have full permiſſion, and all opportunity that may be to doe their worke; neither could the politician have ever made this breach or extended it to that buſineſſe it is at, but for the certaine aſſiſtance of the Clergy, who for that end bound them his inſtruments, by the liberall diſtribution of honours and preferments, by enlargements of dignity &amp; livings by giving them power in Courts, &amp; letting them taſt the ſweets of domination: by authoriſing them in their advance of tithes, multiplying their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, favouring them in their abundant differences, and reſtleſſe lawſuits; and in all likelihood they muſt bee their ſervants who pay them ſuch large wages; info much that in all the time of this Kingdomes ſlavery and wicked mens oppreſſions of us, who were greater promoters of both then the Clergy; what was the politique ſubject of their Sermons then, and diſcourſes, but the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of prerogative, and unlimited ſway; the gayning of eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to themſelves not by their doctrines or lives, for what could be more corrupt and ſcandalous, but by ſubtill deluſions, and deluſive ſophiſmes; the fitting of our minds for ſlavery, the abaſing of our courages againſt injuries in Church or State; by preaching for obedience to all commands good or bad, under
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156186:6"/>deceitfull termes of active and paſſive, by which meanes injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men were heartned in induring miſchiefes, and good men moap'd and ſtupified to a patient ſufferance of them, their very tongues tied up and no liberate given ſo much as to motion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt apparent in juries, or to diſcover to the world the iniquitie of them: This uſe is made of thoſe moſt admirable guifts we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Clergy for, to this good end ſerves their great learning and excellent parts; and as in former times by theſe and many other wayes they onely employed their ſtudies to make us apt and eaſie to admit our ſlavery without grudging or gainſaying, ſo doe they ſtill continue the Stateſmens hirelings, to further that difference betweene the Proteſtant and Puritan, which makes ſo much for their advantage: And that they may be truely ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are brought up in the Univerſities fitted for the purpoſe; no man there countenanced unleſſe he is like to prove a champion againſt the Puritans, the greater their abilities are that way, their preferments are anſwerable, inſomuch, that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally thoſe Miniſters are onely good, that truſting onely to themſelves, and not taking the pleaſing courſe, could expect no encouragement from the Biſhop or others in high places, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contentedly did betake themſelves to ſuch places their honeſt friends and deſerts obtained for them, whereas men of that other ſtraine were almoſt courted into benefices, where the former be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits did not more ſway with to juſtifie injuſtice, and ſow divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, then the longing expectation after greater and greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments; and what though ſome have refuſed preferments, and yet are zealous in your worke; it is well knowne yet that they live in abundance, drinke the ſweet, and eate the fat of the Land, are recompenced with large gifts, and abundant Legacies; who by a cunning refufall of what they need not, and perhaps they thinke would be too troubleſome have taken ſo deepe root in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>watchfull mens minds, that there are none ſo great promoters of this worke as they; who likewiſe being the moſt ſubtill of all the tribe, order the buſineſſe ſo, that what by their abilities of ſpeech, reverent eſtimation men have of their perſons, of their functions, of their ſinceritie, they even delude them as they liſt, and have ſo farre fomented this fire of diſſention that it is to bee ſeared it will very ſhortly breake out into a flame: they have even heightned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156186:7"/>this hatred to an inſurrection, the people riſe up one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, grow into factions and acquaintances by wearing colours, and publike meetings, outfacing authority, and ſlighting the moſt ſoveraigne power, even of the Parliament it ſelfe; nor is this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſhort time to be entinguiſht, though much care be uſed, and great paines taken for the doing it, ſo long as a cunning malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſort of men are ſuffered without controule or juſt puniſhment to yeeld new matter to this deſtructive flame of contention; to curbe the licence, and puniſh the inſolencies of thoſe licentious Clergymen may very well be one of the principall workes of the Parliaments, whoſe earneſt endeavours and noble undertakings doe find no greater oppoſition from any ſort of men, no not from the Cavalier himſelfe, or the Kings evill Councellors, then from theſe men of malice and diſſention; many of them are Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and ſo voted, others likewiſe would appeare to be ſo, did the people thinke it a fit time to make their complaints many of them are of ſcandalous and debaucht lives, all of them indeed are bound by the reſpects they have to their owne ſafetie to deſtroy the Parliament, by whom they know, were they at leaſure they ſhould be ſifted, and their crimes cenſured, and to bring in againe the former government, wherein they found ſo great connivance in all ſorts of vices whatſoever: And now what more ſeaſonable councell can there bee to all ſorts of men, then to try and examine all that they heare, to entertaine nothing for the opinion we have of the man, for the judgement is never ſo likely to be deluded as when the perſon is too highly eſteemed, to ſee likewiſe in how many reſpects the Clergyman is bound to make the Puritan odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Proteſtant, and how greatly diſadvantagious that is to the worke, all honeſt men are bound in conſcience to further, and likewiſe to conclude thoſe Clergy men diſaffected that ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after endeavour it, and to let both them and others in authority know it, to be firme in their affections to the Puritan, paſt all their ſubtilties to diſunite them, that ſo all honeſt men being heartily united, the greater may be their force, and the kingdomes enemies the ſpeedier ſubdued: the Puritan, Sectary, Browniſt, and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters under pretence of railing againſt, doe ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize and defame all the honeſt men of the Kingdome, yea even
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156186:7"/>of the Parliament themſelves: ſo that if we be not the more cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious we may be ſo farre deluded, as to diſeſteeme even their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not for that to any reaſonable diſcreet man they can appeare to be any other then as the actions of the moſt wiſe ſhould bee, but becauſe they are approved of by the honeſt Puritan: It is not ſafe they thinke to rave againſt the Parliament point blanke, they would then indeed appeare ſo palpably malicious and villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly diſaffected, that men would have much adoe to tarry their tryall by Law without doing preſent execution on them: &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore like men full of ſubtlety, they wound the Parliament through the Puritans ſides and therein take ſo vaſt a liberty, that almoſt provokes an honeſt hearted man beyond his patience; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they ſpeake in a doubtfull ſenſe, ſo as that all who are miſled by them can underſtand them, and yet they thinke that if they ſhould be queſtioned, as out of guilt of conſcience they cannot be expect if they ſhall bee able to give ſuch an interpretation to their words, that thereby they can delude the holdfaſt of Law and the cenſure of juſtice: thus they provide an excuſe before they act their villany, and proceed as farre as they imagine that will beare them out; what high time it is that theſe men ſhould bee cruſhed, leaſt in time they ſow ſo many tares in the hearts of men; that no wiſedome of man ſhall be able to plucke up, but that they choake even the ſeeds of good doctrine, and root out of our minds the very principles of reaſon: Another villanous worke they have in hand, is to take away our courages and dull our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions by commending peace unto us, when we are neceſſitated to take up our Swords; what fooles they imagine us to be, as if we did not know what were the ſweets of peace, but then it muſt be accompanied with liberty, the bondman is at peace; there is peace, there is peace in a dungeon, yet I thinke no man can bee heartily in love with ſuch kinde of peace, no certainly, if our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and our religion be much dearer to us then our lives, as I thinke they are to every wiſe man, then ſure they muſt be dearer to us then our reſt, our ſwords are drawne for them, and ſo long as they are violated, what peace? what peace? ſo long as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencies and conſpiracies of unjuſt men, and their uſurpations are ſo many? what peace? ſo long as thoſe that would free us from former oppreſſions, and would provide for our future liberties,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156186:8"/>are in no ſafety but in continuall hazard of their lives? were wee not neceſſitated to it, it were madneſſe to thinke wee could take pleaſure in ſhedding of our owne bloods: what ſhallow men doe they imagine us to be, that thinke, that though their ſweet words, and ſmooth faces, we doe not ſee their fowle and miſchievous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions: yes to their griefe of heart and they joy of all good men they behold that, notwithſtanding they have in many other things deluded us, in this they have not; the <hi>Militia</hi> is ſetled in ſafe and truſty hands, the Forts and ſtrong holds made good, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Navy ſecured and commanded by a faithfull and couragious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of his country, that a ſtrong and a welfurniſhed Army is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the terrour of wicked men and we hope to the ſuppreſſion: they are quite fruſtrate of their ends, all their cunning diſcourſes and ſubtle motions for peace, though delivered with never ſo much pretended piety, and ſeeming love to our ſafeties, come ſhort of their purpoſe, they have not thereby lulled us aſleepe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> us to ſecure, no, we have the courages of men, of valiant provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men upon us, provokt by an inſight into all our injuries, which are now freſh in our memories, provoked by diſcovery of their deluſions, and animated by the amiable ſight of liberty which we may now if we will our ſelves obtaine, of which for many yeares we have beene deprived: and therefore it is not good nor honeſt that they continue their invitations to peace, ſo long as the Parliament ſee it needefull to provide for warre This it is when they will be overwiſe and paſſe the bounds of their office, nor are they more miſtaken in this, then in other matters, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when they plead the Kings cauſe, their engagements and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries here make them ſtarke blind, and let them not ſee how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſtickling for the Kings prerogative they comprehend under that ſuch things, the obtayning whereof if duly conſidered would make his Majeſties office the moſt hazardous, and fraught with leaſt content of any one in the Kingdome. A negative voyce they much ſtand for, a power of calling and likewiſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving Parliaments; theſe things becauſe they carry power with them, and ſee me to adde much greatneſſe and high prerogative to the King, they ſtickling for them, and ſee not that if the King ſhould have them, he would be thereby ever liable to the blame, and cenſures of the people; for if any thing ſhould be conſulted
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156186:8"/>of by the Parliament, and by them concluded to be ſafe and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Kingdome, and that the King by that power they claime for him, ſhould croſſe it if the people ſhould in the time to come by neceſſitie for the want of what the Parliament would have provided for them, and the King would not, whom have they then to blame but the King: and he likewiſe muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie lie under their hard opinions, ſhould the neglect of calling Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments bring oppreſſions upon the people: or the too ſoone diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving them without conſent of the Houſe before their buſineſſe were ully diſpatcht. Both which in their booke of Canons and conſtitutions eccleſiaſticall, where without once mentioning the Parliament, they take liberty to make the Kings Prerogatives what they pleaſe, there I ſay have they peremptorily concluded the power of calling and diſſolving all aſſemblies to bee the Kings undoubted right, and would likewiſe have poſſeſt the people ſo by the quarterly reading of thoſe decrees of theirs in Churches by their owne order: It is true indeed theſe commons are moſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly damned by the Parliament, but by the remembrance hereof we may palpably obſerve, what a power they then uſurpt to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and how notoriouſly they abuſed that power to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the King, his perpetuall hazard and diſquiet: The King paſt all queſtion ſaw all this when he ſo willingly aſſented to thoſe two acts for the conſtant calling of Parliment, and not diſſolution of this, both which the Clergy had no other means to diſanull and make of no effect, then by infuſing into his Majeſties eares, and inſinuating to the people, that the King hath a negative voyce by which all that the Parliament ſhall doe comes to nothing, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it pleaſes the King to aſſent, which is not like to be but when thoſe that are ſo powerfull (his evill counſellers) over him ſhall give way to; by which meanes alone thoſe evill men have a power of croſſing and making voyd all the debates and concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Parliament, and though this bee in effect to make the ſafety and freedome of the people to depend upon one mans will &amp; underſtanding, an abſurdity in government; a man would think theſe men could not have the impudence to plead for, much leſſe that the people ſhould be ſo unadviſed as to admit it to enter their thoughts as a thing iuſt and reaſonable, yet indeed ſo impudent are thoſe as to plead for it, and ſo ignoran, are the people, as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156186:9"/>to admit it, which is the ground and occaſion of all the evils and miſchiefes which at this day threaten both his Maieſty and the whole people. So that wee ſee the King hath little to thank them for their too haſty forwardneſſe in clayming what is ſo unſafe for him, and ſo likely to divide the affections of the people from him: But what care they, the King getting power, they get advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, credit, honour, and what not? ſo little reſpect they what is ſafe for him or prejudiciall to the people, ſo their owne ends bee ſerved; there comes no harme from good conſideration, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice then cannot be amiſſe, to wiſh every one to conſider what they heare, to examine all not timorouſly, nor prejudicially, but impartially by that uncorrupt rules of reaſon, and to give no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to what is ſpoken for the credit or eſtimation of the ſpeaker, but becauſe it is the truth, and nothing but the truth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
